<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Deployment_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Deployment_Guide-Authentication_and_Authorization">
    <title>Authentication and Authorization</title>
    <para>
        The use of Cyrus IMAP may have a significant impact on the design, use and load of the current authentication and authorization infrastructure.
    </para>
    <para>
        Most commonly, an organisation has existing LDAP or SQL-based AAA infrastructure, that scales up sufficiently to service all components of said infrastructure with at least authentication and authorization.
    </para>
    <section id="sect-Deployment_Guide-Authentication_and_Authorization-Users_and_Mailboxes">
        <title>Users and Mailboxes</title>
        <para>
            User mailboxes have an identifier which is not necessarily the same as the login name used. There are three distinguishable aspects to a user&#39;s entity and the mailbox associated with it;
        </para>
        <para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The user login credentials that are associated with the user authentication entity and verify the user is who the user claims to be.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        For example, the user logs in with username <code>john.doe@example.org</code> and password <code>verysecret</code>.
                    </para>

                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The user&#39;s authentication entity &mdash;with all attributes associated with it&mdash; can have one of those attributes be used to create the relationship between the user authentication entity on the one side, and the mailbox entity on the other side.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        For example, the user that authenticated as <code>john.doe@example.org</code> may have a mailbox named <code>jdoe</code>.
                    </para>

                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The authorization entity, used to assign certain permissions to the user, uses the same attribute used to determine the mailbox name.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        For example, the user that authenticated as <code>john.doe@example.com</code> and has mailbox <code>jdoe</code> needs an access control list entry on that mailbox that assigns <code>jdoe</code> certain rights on said mailbox.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

        </para>

    </section>
    

</chapter>

