<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Administrator_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Administrator_Guide-Access_Control">
    <title>Access Control</title>
    <section id="sect-Administrator_Guide-Access_Control-Access_Rights">
        <title>Access Rights</title>
        <para>
            Access rights in Cyrus IMAP are &ndash;or should be&ndash; fully compatible with <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4314">RFC 4314</ulink>.
        </para>
        <variablelist id="vari-Administrator_Guide-Access_Rights-Access_Rights_available_in_Cyrus_IMAP">
            <title>Access Rights available in Cyrus IMAP</title>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>l</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>lookup</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The subject can <emphasis>lookup</emphasis> this folder, and see that the folder exists, meaning the folder will appear in a <code>LIST "" "*"</code>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Folders to which the subject has no lookup rights may still be subscribed to. The lookup right is only required if Cyrus IMAP has been configured with the <literal>allowallsubscribe</literal> setting to <literal>false</literal> (0). In Cyrus IMAP &PRODUCT_VERSION;, this setting defaults to <literal>false</literal> (0). In a Cyrus IMAP Murder, this setting is typically set to <literal>true</literal> (1).
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The <literal>l</literal> can be assigned to a folder, without the <literal>l</literal> right having been given out for the parent folder. Cyrus IMAP will pretend the parent folder does not exist;
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <example id="exam-Administrator_Guide-Access_Rights_available_in_Cyrus_IMAP-Example_Client_Server_Session_with_l_Right_on_Subfolder_Only">
                            <title>Example Client - Server Session with <literal>l</literal> Right on Subfolder Only</title>
                            <para>
                                <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4314">RFC 4314</ulink>, section 4., page 13, states the following example:
                            </para>
                            <para>
                                <blockquote>
                                    <para>
                                        Note that if the user has <literal>l</literal> right to a mailbox "A/B", but not to its parent mailbox "A", the LIST command should behave as if the mailbox "A" doesn't exist, for example:
                                    </para>
                                    <para>

<screen>
C: A777 LIST "" *
S: * LIST (\NoInferiors) "/" "A/B"
S: * LIST () "/" "C"
S: * LIST (\NoInferiors) "/" "C/D"
S: A777 OK LIST completed
</screen>

                                    </para>

                                </blockquote>

                            </para>

                        </example>

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>r</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>read</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The subject can read the contents of this folder, meaning that the subject is allowed to <command>SELECT</command> or <command>EXAMINE</command> the folder, query its <command>STATUS</command>, <command>FETCH</command> data, <command>SEARCH</command> the contents, and <command>COPY</command> contents from the folder.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>s</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>seen</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The subject is permitted to maintain the subject's seen state for this folder, or the shared seen state in case the <literal>/vendor/cmu/cyrus-imapd/sharedseen</literal> has been set to <literal>true</literal> (see <command>mboxconfig</command> in <xref linkend="chap-Administrator_Guide-cyradm" />). Additionally, the <emphasis>\Recent</emphasis> flags are preserved for the subject.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>w</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>write</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The subject is permitted to <emphasis>write</emphasis> to the folder, actually meaning the subject is permitted to maintain flags and keywords other then <emphasis>\Seen</emphasis> and <emphasis>\Deleted</emphasis>, which are controlled using the <literal>s</literal> and <literal>t</literal> rights respectively.
                    </para>
                    <note>
                        <title>IMAP Clients</title>
                        <para>
                            IMAP clients may expect to be able to set flags other then <emphasis>\Seen</emphasis> and <emphasis>\Deleted</emphasis> and attempt to set those flags immediately along with a "Mark as read" action, without the subject actually being permitted to set some of those flags through the <literal>w</literal> right.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4314">RFC 4314</ulink>, section 4., page 15, states that the server SHOULD NOT fail, as the tagged NO response is not handled very will by deployed clients. In order to comply, we have <ulink url="https://bugzilla.cyrusimap.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3488">Bug #3488</ulink>, as Cyrus IMAP currently does seem to issue a tagged NO response.
                        </para>

                    </note>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>i</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>insert</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        A subject is permitted to <emphasis>insert</emphasis> content into a folder, meaning the subject may <command>COPY</command> messages with this folder as the target folder, and may <command>APPEND</command> messages to this folder.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>p</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>post</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The <emphasis>post</emphasis> right currently is exclusive to Cyrus IMAP, and allows the subject to send email to the submission address for the mailbox.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This right differs from the <literal>i</literal> right in that the delivery system inserts trace information into submitted messages.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Example implementations using the <literal>p</literal> right include shared folders to which specific recipient addresses are delivered through LMTP pre-authorized as the <literal>postuser</literal>, which must then also have the <literal>p</literal> right on the target folder.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>c</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>create</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The <emphasis>create</emphasis> right is a right introduced with <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2086">RFC 2086</ulink> (IMAP4 ACL extension), indicating the subject's right to create new sub-folders in the parent folder on which this right has been assigned, but also to delete the same folder.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Since <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4314">RFC 4314</ulink>, the <literal>c</literal> right has been replaced with the <literal>k</literal> right to <command>CREATE</command> folders with, the <literal>x</literal> right to <command>DELETE</command> folders with.
                    </para>
                    <important>
                        <title>The <literal>c</literal> should no longer be used</title>
                        <para>
                            Even though Cyrus IMAP is backwards compatible when it comes to the <literal>c</literal> right, which it implements as implying as the <literal>k</literal> right, implementations should not count on the <literal>c</literal> right backwards compability to be around forever, and to fully implement the legacy <literal>c</literal> right, use <literal>kx</literal>.
                        </para>

                    </important>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>k</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The subject has the right to <command>CREATE</command> a new folder if the <literal>k</literal> exists on the parent folder of the folder created.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The rights required for a <command>RENAME</command> to be successful could be illustrated by describing a <command>RENAME</command> as a <command>CREATE</command> of the new folder, not exactly followed by a <command>COPY</command> on the old folder's contents, but more like a move like on a filesystem, and finally a <command>DELETE</command> on the old folder.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        As such, the <literal>k</literal> is the right required on the parent folder of the target folder, and the <literal>x</literal> right on the source folder. To further illustrate;
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <example id="exam-Administrator_Guide-Access_Rights_available_in_Cyrus_IMAP-Example_Client_Session_with_RENAME">
                            <title>Example Client Session with RENAME</title>
                            <para>
                                Suppose the subject has the <literal>k</literal> right on folder "C/", and the <literal>x</literal> right on folder "A/B", then a RENAME A/B C/B would succeed.
                            </para>

                        </example>

                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>a</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>administer</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The subject is allowed to administer the folder, meaning the subject is allowed to perform administrative operations on the folder. The <literal>a</literal> right is needed to successfully execute <command>SETACL</command>, <command>DELETEACL</command> (short for <command>SETACL ""</command>) and to execute <command>GETACL</command> or <command>LISTRIGHTS</command>.
                    </para>
                    <note>
                        <title>IMAP Clients</title>
                        <para>
                            IMAP clients may issue a <command>GETACL</command> in order to obtain the subject's rights on the folder, where they should be using <command>MYRIGHTS</command>, as <command>GETACL</command> or <command>LISTRIGHTS</command> return the full Access Control List, including other subject's identifiers.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                            Unless the subject has the <literal>a</literal> right on a folder, issuing a <command>GETACL</command> or <command>LISTRIGHTS</command> will cause Cyrus IMAP to send a tagged "NO: Permission denied" response if the subject has the <literal>l</literal> (lookup) right on the folder, and a "NO: No Such Mailbox" response otherwise, as per seciont 8. of RFC 2086 and section 6. of RFC 4314 &ndash; both conveniently called "Security Considerations".
                        </para>

                    </note>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>x</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        use this to indicate the subject has the right to delete the mailbox, as opposed to 'c' or 'd'
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>t</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The subject is allowed to delete messages from this folder, meaning that the subject is allowed to flag messages as deleted.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        In IMAP, messages are only actually deleted in a way that at least makes them invisible to the folder's users need to be expunged. For the corresponding <command>EXPUNGE</command> however, the <literal>x</literal> right is required.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>e</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>expunge</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The subject is allowed to <emphasis>expunge</emphasis> messages in this folder, meaning the subject has the right to remove all messages that have been flagged as deleted from all visibility.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        In IMAP, expunging messages only applies to messages flagged as deleted. For the subject to be able to flag messages as deleted, the however, the <literal>t</literal> right is required.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        We say "remove from all visibility", because the implementation of expunging messages in Cyrus IMAP is subject to the <literal>expunge_mode</literal> in <filename>/etc/imapd.conf</filename>, which when set to <literal>delayed</literal> only causes the reference to the expunged messages to be deleted from the folder index database &ndash;effectively removing the expunged message(s) from all visibility, while they remain in place on the Cyrus IMAP server filesystem.
                    </para>
                    <note>
                        <title>IMAP Clients</title>
                        <para>
                            IMAP clients may expect to be able to <command>EXPUNGE</command> a folder regardless of the availability of this right.
                        </para>

                    </note>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>d</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Stands for <literal>delete</literal>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        This is the legacy, <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2086">RFC 2086</ulink> access control right for the <emphasis>delete</emphasis> right. In versions of Cyrus IMAP implementing only this right, subjects were allowed to flag messages as deleted and expunge folders.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        The <emphasis>delete</emphasis> right has been split in to three separate rights, <literal>t</literal> (flag messages as deleted), <literal>e</literal> (expunge folder) and <literal>k</literal> (delete folder).
                    </para>
                    <note>
                        <title><literal>deleteright</literal> setting</title>
                        <para>
                            The <literal>deleteright</literal> setting in <filename>/etc/imapd.conf</filename> controls the <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2086">RFC 2086</ulink> right which controls whether or not the subject may delete a folder. However, this setting (as the original specification for the delete right was considered ambiguous) is ignored, and if it is set to <literal>c</literal>, is automatically converted to the <literal>x</literal> right.
                        </para>

                    </note>

                </listitem>

            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

    </section>

    <section id="sect-Administrator_Guide-Access_Control-Combining_Access_Rights">
        <title>Combining Access Rights</title>
        <para>
            para
        </para>

    </section>

    <section id="sect-Administrator_Guide-Access_Control-Access_Right_Identifiers">
        <title>Access Right Identifiers</title>
        <para>
            para
        </para>
        <para>
            note on authentication vs. authorization
        </para>
        <para>
            note on group identifiers, canonification, ptloader and invalid identifiers
        </para>
        <para>
            note on cross-realm
        </para>

    </section>

    <section id="sect-Administrator_Guide-Access_Control-Default_Access_Control_Information_on_New_Folders">
        <title>Default Access Control Information on New Folders</title>
        <para>
            para
        </para>

    </section>

    <section id="sect-Administrator_Guide-Access_Control-GETACL_and_MYRIGHTS">
        <title>GETACL and MYRIGHTS</title>
        <para>
            para
        </para>

    </section>


</chapter>

